Louise Foucar Marshall and Tom Marshall Collection, 1888-1972 (bulk 1900-1953)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Louise Foucar Marshall and Tom Marshall collection, 1888-1972 bulk 1900-1953
Collection Number: MS 452
Marshall,Louise Foucar; Marshall, Thomas K. (Thomas Keith)
Documents and photographs, 1888-1972 (bulk 1900-1953). This collection is comprised of documents and photographs relating to the lives of Louise Foucar Marshall and her husband Tom Marshall. The bulk of the material consists of her personal correspondence and memorabilia, property records, official documents and correspondence relating to the Marshall Charitable Foundation, which they founded in 1930, and documents relating to Tom’s death and Louise’s trial for his murder in 1931. The collection also includes a large number of photographs and negatives, including some glass-plate negatives, taken by Tom Marshall of the University of Arizona and the city of Tucson in the early years of the 20th century.
4 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Louise Henriette Foucar was born in 1864, the daughter of a wealthy Boston family that had emigrated from Germany. Louise studied in France, Italy and Switzerland but her health was poor and she searched for a place with a better climate to live. After stints in El Paso, Texas and Mexico City, in 1890 she moved to Denver, Colorado and earned two degrees at the University of Denver. While in Denver, she developed tuberculosis and heart problems and in 1898 she moved again, this time to the warmer climate and lower elevation of Tucson.
She came to the University of Arizona as a graduate student in the academic year of 1898-1899; she became an instructor the next year and in 1900, at the age of 36, she became the school’s first woman professor. She taught Botany and a host of languages, including English, French, Latin and Spanish, and in 1901 she was named head of the Department of Ancient and Modern Languages.
Louise began to buy and develop properties near the expanding university campus using money inherited from her parents and in 1903, she resigned her teaching position at the university to focus full time on her business pursuits.
In 1904, she married Thomas Marshall, a former student, in El Paso, Texas. They lived in the brick house Louise built on a large two-acre lot on East Second St. in Tucson, Arizona.
In addition to developing and managing residential properties Louise developed a block of businesses across from the university’s main entrance that became Tucson’s first suburban shopping center, University Square. She owned and managed a gift shop located in the square and was appointed by the Governor to serve on the Arizona Board of Regents.
Louise continued to develop properties and she and Tom used the growing revenue to create the private, not-for-profit corporation known as Marshall Charitable Foundation on Jan. 16, 1930. They created the first private foundation in Arizona, one that would, in Louise’s words, “carry on our work when we are gone.”
Despite Louise’s business success, her marriage to Tom began to deteriorate. There were persistent rumors about his affair with an ex-housekeeper and the mysterious cause of Louise’s prolonged illness. After weeks of tests, doctors finally determined that she had been poisoned. On the night of April 27, 1931 Louise shot her husband four times at point blank range.
Thomas Marshall died three weeks later at a Los Angeles hospital and Louise was charged with first-degree murder. The trial became a media sensation, attracting newspaper coverage and bold headlines around the country. Louise pleaded guilty by reason of temporary insanity, one the very first legal cases to include this novel defense, claiming that she shot her husband because of fear that she was being poisoned. The jury acquitted her on the first-degree murder charge after deliberating less than half an hour.
After her acquittal, Louise rededicated herself to managing her extensive real estate holdings and promoting the work of the new Marshall Charitable Foundation. She took over day-to-day operations and began working in concert with a newly-appointed board of directors. Her participation in foundation activities continued until her death in 1956 at the age of 92. When she died Louise Marshall bequeathed her personal property to Wilma Peters, widow of Ivan Peters, the Marshall’s longtime property manager, Foundation president, and personal friend. After Mrs. Peters died her daughter Patricia Stephenson maintained the collection.
Thomas Keith Marshall was born on August 3, 1870 in Kansas. After leaving home he traveled around the country, working first as a farm laborer, then a miner. In 1899 he ended up at the University of Arizona where he enrolled, at the age of 29, in the preparatory department because of his lack of a high school record. While at the University Tom played on the first football team ever fielded by the University of Arizona and found a job on campus as a gardener and laborer. Tom also became an avid photographer during this time. In 1903 he began working as a maintenance man for Professor Louise Foucar and she soon named him manager for her growing real estate holdings. He left the University in 1903 without ever earning a degree.
In 1904 Tom proposed marriage to Louise and she accepted. They were quietly married in El Paso. Early in their marriage the Marshalls worked on several joint business projects together. In the early teens, Tom and Louise began to grow apart and each became more engrossed in their own pursuits, in Tom’s case journalism and then later, politics. He served as a delegate to launch the Roosevelt candidacy, and became active in Arizona state politics as a member of the Progressive Party. He became active in the temperance movement and enjoyed traveling all over the state to give talks on both Progressive politics and the temperance movement. In 1915, he wrote and published a 73 page book entitled, Prohibition in Arizona: The First Six Months of Prohibition in Arizona and its Effect Upon Industry, Savings and Municipal Government.
Just after midnight on April 27, 1931 Louise Marshall shot her husband with a small caliber pistol while he lay sleeping. Tom was immediately taken to a local hospital and then later transferred to a hospital in Los Angeles, where he developed an infection after an unsuccessful operation to remove one of the bullets. He died on May 20, 1931.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into 6 series.
Series I: Personal, 1888-1956
Series II: Marshall Foundation and Properties, 1904-1972
Series III: Death of Tom Marshall and Trial 1931-1934
Series IV: Photographs, 1890-1970
Series V: Indexes to the Collection, 1888-1972
Series VI: Oversize materials 1894-1953
Scope and Content Note
Documents and photographs, 1888-1972 (bulk 1900-1953). This collection is comprised of documents relating to the lives of Louise Foucar Marshall and her husband Tom Marshall. The bulk of the material consists of her personal correspondence and memorabilia, documents relating to Tom’s death and Louise’s trial for his murder in 1931, and to the Marshalls’ real estate holdings. Louise Marshall was instrumental in the development of numerous residential properties and businesses in the area surrounding the University of Arizona. The collection includes personal letters, diaries written by Louise and Tom Marshall, journals and business letters, and books and pamphlets collected by Louise Marshall. Official documents and correspondence relating to the non-profit foundation, the Marshall Charitable Foundation, are also included here. This collection also includes a large number of photographs taken by Tom Marshall of the University of Arizona and the city of Tucson in the early years of the 20th century, which include university buildings, Tucson hospitals and sanitariums, and street scenes. It also includes a T. Roosevelt 1912 Progressive ticket battle flag and a large number of photographs and negatives, including some 4 x 5 glass-plate negatives.
Access Terms
Marshall, Louise Henriette Foucar
Marshall, Thomas K. (Thomas Keith),
Peters, Ivan
Peters, Wilma
Seymour, Harriet
Trials (Murder) – Arizona
Tucson (Ariz.) – History
Tucson (Ariz.) – Pictorial works
University of Arizona – Pictorial works
Marshall Charitable Foundation
Marshall Foundation
Container List
- Series I: Personal,1888-1956
  This series is subdivided by document type, arranged alphabetically, then chronologically. It contains correspondence, financial and personal documents and memorabilia.
  - Subseries 1: Correspondence, 1888-1972
    - Invitations and announcements, 1888-1953 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Louise F. Marshall, 1909-1929 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Louise F. Marshall, 1930-1939 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Louise F. Marshall, 1940-1949 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Louise F. Marshall, 1950-1952 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Louise F. Marshall, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Louise F. Marshall, 1954-1956 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Thomas K. Marshall, 1911-1929 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Peters Family, 1927-1959 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Peters Family, 1960-1972 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Subseries 2: Financial Documents, 1903-1957
    - Estate, Louise F. Marshall, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Estate, Tom Marshall, 1931-1945 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Personal finance, 1903-1954 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Wills, Louise F. Marshall, 1920-1952 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Subseries 3: Various personal documents, 1900-1956
    - Family, Louise F. Marshall, 1900-1931 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Louise Marshall obituaries, 1953-1956 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Memorabilia, 1911-1943 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - University of Arizona, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Series 2: Marshall Foundation & Properties, 1904-1972
  This series is arranged alphabetically and contains official documents of the Foundation, correspondence, deeds, mortgages and rental reports.
  - 1227 E. 2nd Street, 1935-1942 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Articles of incorporation, resolutions and by-laws, 1904-1972 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Business correspondence, 1927-1949 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Business correspondence, 1950-1972 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Conveyance of property, 1937-1944 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Deeds and mortgages, 1904-1929 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Deeds and mortgages, 1930-1939 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Deeds and mortgages, 1940-1947 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Deeds of trust, 1937-1944 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Lease agreements, 1904-1946 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Meeting minutes, 1937-1967 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Property correspondence, 1942-1945 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Property expenses, 1925-1959 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Rental reports, 1927-1929 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Rental reports, 1930-1934 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Rental reports, 1935-1939 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Rental reports, 1940-1944 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Rental reports, 1945-1949 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - University Gift Shop, 1944-1948 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Death of Tom Marshall and Trial, 1931-1934
  This series consists of photographs taken by Tom Marshall of the University of Arizona, the city of Tucson and its surrounding area, and parts of the western United States. It is subdivided into prints, negatives, and glass-plate negatives.
  - Correspondence, Louise F. Marshall, 1931 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, Tom Marshall, 1931 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Evidence and trial preparation, 1931 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Legal and court documents, 1931-1934 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Medical records of Tom Marshall, 1931 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Slander suit, Seymour vs. Marshall, 1931-1932 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Statements, Louise F, Marshall, 1931 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Photographs,1890-1970
  - Subseries 1: Prints,1890-1970
    - Marshalls: Art of Louise F. Marshall, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Marshalls: Family, friends and pets, 1904-1930 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Marshalls: Family of Tom Marshall, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Marshalls: Tom and Louise F. Marshall, 1901-1920 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Marshall home and properties: Commercial and civic properties, 1922-1944 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Marshall home and properties: Cottage behind Marshall home, 1911-1915 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Marshall home and properties: Houses and apartments, 1906-1929 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Marshall home and properties: Marshall home, 1911-1915 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Marshall home and properties: University neighborhood, 1905-1930 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Tucson and surrounding area: Businesses, 1915-1920 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Tucson and surrounding area: Churches, 1915-1920 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Tucson and surrounding area: Civic buildings and clubs, 1910-1924 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Tucson and surrounding area: Homes, 1910-1920 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Tucson and surrounding area: Hospitals and sanitariums, 1911-1920 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Tucson and surrounding area: Railroad, 1915-1920 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Tucson and surrounding area: Schools, 1920 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Tucson and surrounding area: Street scenes, 1911-1921 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Tucson and surrounding area: Surrounding area and desert, 1903-1920 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Tucson and surrounding area: Unidentified (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - University of Arizona: Campus structures and scenes, 1894-1925 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - University of Arizona: Classroom buildings, 1915-1930 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - University of Arizona: East and West Cottages and Presidents home, 1894-1900 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - University of Arizona: Library/Museum, 1920 (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - University of Arizona: Military barracks, 1918 (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - University of Arizona: Mines and Engineering Building, 1915-1922 (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - University of Arizona: North Hall, 1900-1916 (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - University of Arizona: Old Main, 1900-1922 (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - University of Arizona: Residence and dining halls, 1910-1920 (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - University of Arizona: South Hall and Herring Hall, 1900-1913 (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - University of Arizona: Steward Observatory, 1920 (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - University of Arizona: Students, 1890-1910 (Box 6, Folder 31)
    - University of Arizona: University entrances, 1910-1924 (Box 6, Folder 32)
    - Western United States: Colorado, 1920 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Western United States: New Mexico and Northern Arizona, 1911-1920 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Western United States: Northern California, 1911 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Western United States: Southern California, 1911-1915 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Western United States: Southern California coast, 1911 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Western United States: Unidentified locations, 1920 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Subseries 2: Negatives,1900-1922
    - Marshalls: Friends, relatives and pets, 1911-1920 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Marshalls: Tom and Louise F. Marshall, 1901-1920 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Marshall home and properties: Commercial properties, 1922 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Marshall home and properties: Cottage behind Marshall home, 1911-1915 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Marshall home and properties: Houses and apartments, 1905-1920 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Marshall home and properties: Marshall home, 1910-1920 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Marshall home and properties: University neighborhood, 1904-1920 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Tucson and surrounding area: Businesses, 1920 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Tucson and surrounding area: Churches, 1915-1920 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Tucson and surrounding area: Civic buildings and clubs, 1920 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Tucson and surrounding area: Homes, 1910-1920 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Tucson and surrounding area: Hospitals and sanitariums, 1920 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Tucson and surrounding area: Railroad, 1915-1920 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Tucson and surrounding area: Schools, 1920 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Tucson and surrounding area: Street scenes, 1911-1920 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - Tucson and surrounding area: Surrounding area and desert, 1911-1920 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - University of Arizona: Campus structures and scenes, 1903-1920 (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - University of Arizona: Classroom buildings, 1915-1920 (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - University of Arizona: Library/Museum, 1920 (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - University of Arizona: Mines and Engineering Building, 1920 (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - University of Arizona: North Hall, South Hall, Herring Hall, 1910-1916 (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - University of Arizona: Old Main, 1900-1920 (Box 7, Folder 28)
    - University of Arizona: Residence and dining halls, 1910-1920 (Box 7, Folder 29)
    - University of Arizona: Steward Observatory, 1920 (Box 7, Folder 30)
    - University of Arizona: Students, 1900-1910 (Box 7, Folder 31)
    - University of Arizona: University entrances, 1919-1920 (Box 7, Folder 32)
    - Western United States: California parks, monuments and fountains, 1911-1920 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Western United States: Colorado, 1920 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Western United States: New Mexico and Northern Arizona, 1920 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Western United States: Ramona’s Marriage Place, San Diego, 1911 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Western United States: San Francisco and Northern California, 1911-1920 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Western United States: Southern California, 1911-1920 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Western United States: Southern California coast, 1911 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Western United States: Unidentified locations, 1911 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Subseries 3: Glass plate negatives, 1911
    - Marshall home, 1911 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - People and pets, 1911 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Southern California, 1911 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Tucson and surrounding area: Surrounding area and desert, 1911 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Tucson and surrounding area: Tucson Depot, 1911 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Tucson and surrounding area: University neighborhood, 1911 (Box 9, Folder 14)
- Series V: Indexes to the Collection,1556-1972
  This collection, as it was maintained by Patricia Stephenson, was originally housed in a series of 3-ring binders and some large boxes containing folders and loose items. This series consists of her inventory and original organization of those items, along with some personal notes. The original notebook and item numbering for each item is noted either on the sleeve for or the reverse of each item.
  - Binders, 1888-1972 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Boxes, 1556-1957 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Photographs, 1890-1970 (Box 8, Folder 17)
- Series VI: Oversized materials,1894-1953
  This series consists of various items including mounted photographs, account books, Louise F. Marshall’s diplomas from the University of Denver, Louise and Tom’s marriage service book, and a Teddy Roosevelt 1912 Progressive ticket battle flag.
  - Oversize materials, 1894-1953 (Box 9, Folder 1)